Hello everybody, thanks for having me today.
أهلًا بكم، شكرًا على استضافتي هنا اليوم.
I'm a little bit injured,
أنا مصاب إصابة بسيطة،
but it takes more than a car to stop me from talking to you.
ولكن يتطلب الأمر أكثر من حادثة سيارة لمنعي من التحدث إليكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Maybe a tank?
ربما دبابة؟
So today, I want to talk about the microprinter,
اليوم، سأتحدث عن الطابعة متناهية الصغر،
about my work, how everything started,
وحول عملي، كيف بدأ كل شيء،
what was my motivation to build the smallest 3-D printer in the world.
وما كان الدافع لي لتصميم أصغر طابعة ثلاثية الأبعاد في العالم؟
Let's start with my daily business.
دعونا نبدأ بالعمل اليومي.
So, my normal working field is called two-photon polymerization.
مجال عملي اليومي يسمي بلمرة الفوتون الثنائية.
It sounds very nerdy, it is very nerdy.
يبدو أنه عمل غريب الأطوار، إنه غريب الأطوار بالفعل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What do you need for making this stuff?
ما الذي تحتاجه لعمل هذه الأشياء؟
You need a complex laser system,
تحتاج نظام ليزر معقد،
a so-called femtosecond laser system,
والذي يسمي نظام ليزر الفيمتو ثانية،
which you focus onto a very tiny spot -- very, very, very tiny --
والذي تركز فيه علي بقعة صغيرة جدا، صغيرة جدا جدا،
and this is a very expensive, not very durable laser system. (Laughs)
وهذا باهظ الثمن، وليس نظام ليزر دائم. (ضحك)
And on the other hand, you need a very complex positioning system.
ومن ناحية أخرى، ستحتاج لنظام تحديد مواقع معقد جدًا.
We call it "Agathe," because it's very heavy,
ونسميه "أجاثا"، لأنه ثقيل جدًا،
and we thought Agathe was a nice name.
ونعتقد أن أجاثا اسم لطيف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And, well, you need this system to move the laser through,
حسنًا، تحتاج هذا النظام ليعبر الليزر من خلاله،
for example, at the very accurate level, about 200 nanometers,
علي سبيل المثال، في مستوى دقيق للغاية، حوالي 200 نانومتر،
so very accurate.
إذًا فهو دقيق جدًا.
And, well, what can you do with that?
حسنًا، ماذا يمكننا أن نفعل به؟
You can do things that you cannot see with your eyes.
يمكنك أن تصنع أشياء لا تستطيع رؤيتها بعينيك.
So you can print out whatever you want,
يمكنك أن تطبع كل ما تريد،
you can print out a tower bridge, you can print out Agathe's husband ...
يمكنك طباعة جسر البرج، وزوج أجاثا...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
OK, but, what makes it so mind-blowing?
ولكن، ما الذي يجعلها تخطف العقول؟
You maybe notice this scale bar, and it's 100 microns for the tower bridge
يمكنك أن تلاحظ شريط القياس هذا، وأنها 100 ميكرون لجسر البرج
and 20 microns for the fat man.
و20 ميكرون للرجل السمين.
For comparison, the diameter of a human hair is around 50 microns.
علي سبيل المقارنة، قطر الشعر البشري حوالي 50 ميكرون.
So these objects are like a dust particle or even smaller,
لذلك هذه العناصر مثل جسيم الغبار أو أصغر،
so you can hardly see them.
لذلك تصعب رؤيتها.
What you can also do and what we are also working on
إن ما نفعله وما نعمل عليه
is improving the system, improving the resins,
هو تطوير النظام، وتطوير الراتنجات،
the material we use for catching a worm or something else.
المواد التي نستخدمها لاصطياد دودة أو شيء آخر.
Inside the resin, we move the laser through the resin, it gets polymerized,
بداخل الراتنج، عند تحرك الليزر بداخل الراتنج يتم بلمرتها،
and we catch a living animal,
وقد أمسكنا بحيوان علي قيد الحياة،
here, a special worm.
ها هي، دودة خاصة.
What we're trying to do, or what the next step would be,
ما نحاول القيام به، أو خطوتنا التالية،
is to make biocompatible polymers and maybe to write some things
هي صنع البوليمرات الحيوية وربما كتابة بعض الأشياء
inside your body or inside the body of a worm,
بداخل جسدك أو بداخل جسد الدودة،
or to attach cells to our structures, and so on.
أو إرفاق الخلايا إلي هياكلنا، وما إلى ذلك.
But, OK, that's my normal working field.
ولكن، هذا هو مجال عملي الطبيعي.
Today I want to tell the story behind the microprinter.
اليوم أريد أن أحدثكم عن قصة الطابعة متناهية الصغر.
What was my motivation?
وماذا كانت دوافعي؟
Well, everything started on Monday morning, 6:30.
بدأ كل شيء يوم الإثنين في الساعة 6:30 صباحًا،
OK, that's a lie. Maybe it was 10 o'clock.
حسنًا، هذه كذبة، ربما كانت الساعة العاشرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I went to my laser lab, which is located near Karlsplatz, in Freihaus,
ذهبت لمعمل الليزر الخاص بي، الذي يقع بالقرب من كارلبلاتس، فريهوس،
at the Vienna University of Technology.
في جامعة فيينا للتقنية.
I went in, and I saw that this laser system was broken,
وعند دخول المختبر اكتشفت أن نظام الليزر كان معطلًا.
and I tried to fix it.
وحاولت إصلاحه.
It took me half a day, several hours.
استغرق الأمر نصف اليوم، عدة ساعات.
Then I noticed, OK, there is a major issue with the pump source.
ثم لاحظت أن هناك مشكلة كبيرة في مصدر الضخ.
I cannot fix that myself; we have to call the service technician.
لا أستطيع إصلاحها بنفسي، مما استدعى حضور فنّي الخدمة.
And from that point on, I noticed I had time to think.
ووقتها لاحظت أنني أملك الوقت للتفكير.
So I thought, "What to do now? Maybe start to write my PhD thesis."
لذلك فكرت، "ماذا أفعل الآن؟ ربما كتابة رسالة الدكتوراه الخاصة بي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
No, no, not a good idea at all.
لا،لا، ليست فكرة جيدة على الإطلاق.
So I started thinking, maybe write a scientific paper.
لذلك بدأت بالتفكير بكتابة ورقة علمية.
Not a good idea at all.
ليست فكرة جيدة إطلاقا.
And then, on Saturday, after a week of thinking,
ويوم السبت، بعد أسبوع من التفكير،
I came up with the idea
خطرت لي الفكرة
to build the smallest 3-D microprinter in the world.
لبناء أصغر طابعة ثلاثية الأبعاد في العالم على الإطلاق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or, the smallest 3-D printer in the world.
أو أصغر طابعة ثلاثية الأبعاد في العالم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So I called my professor and told him about it.
لذلك قمت بالاتصال بأستاذي وأخبرته بذلك.
"Hey, let's build the thing! I have time. Is it OK?"
"هيا نصمم ذلك الشيء! أنا لدي الوقت. هل ابدأ؟"
"Go ahead, build it."
"امض قدمًا، قم ببنائها؟"
And so I went to the university, and from that point on,
ولذلك ذهبت للجامعة وانطلاقا من هذه النقطة،
I just put everything out of my brain inside the computer
قمت بتسجيل كل ما يدور داخل عقلي داخل الحاسب الآلي
to make this CAD construction of the whole thing.
لعمل التصميم للأمر بأكمله.
And after a few months, we had the first test run with the system.
وبعد بضعة أشهر، كنا نجري أول اختبار تشغيل للنظام.
It worked brilliantly from the first test on,
وكانت النتائج مبهرة مع أول اختبار،
and it had the same resolution as systems which cost 60,000 euros,
وكانت له نفس درجة الثبات مثل النظام الذي يتكلف 60,000 يورو،
and we only spent 1,500 euros for the system,
وأنفقنا 1,500 يورو فقط على هذا النظام،
not including my salary,
لا يشمل راتبي،
but that wouldn't add so much on its own.
لكن هذا لم يزد التكلفة كثيرًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
OK, how does this work?
حسنًا، كيف يعمل هذا؟
I brought you a video
لقد أحضرت لكم عرض مصور
where you can see how you can put in your three-dimensional file.
حيث يمكنكم رؤية كيف يمكن الإضافة في الملف ثلاثي الأبعاد.
This video was produced by a friend of mine, Junior Veloso.
لقد تم إنتاج هذا العرض التصويري بواسطة صديقي جونيور ويلوسو.
And you can see, you have a set stage which moves up.
كما تشاهدون، لديكم قاعدة متحركة ترتفع صعودا.
And under the set stage, there is a liquid,
يوجد سائل تحت القاعدة،
which gets solidified by the light.
والذي يتم تجميده بواسطة الضوء.
And slice by slice, you create the model,
وشريحة فوق الأخرى، يتم إنشاء النموذج،
so you really pull it out of the liquid.
ثم يتم إخراجهم من السائل.
And it just depends on how big your model is.
وتعتمد فقط علي حجم النموذج.
Maybe you have 100 slices, 1,000 or 10,000 slices.
ربما يكون لديك 100 شريحة، 1,000 أو 10,000 شريحة،
So that's how it works.
هذه طريقة عمله.
Of course, this is a much bigger machine than the microprinter,
بالطبع، هذه آلة أكبر من الطابعة البالغة الصغر،
but it uses more or less the same principles,
ولكنها تستعمل المبادئ نفسها،
so that's what I want to show you.
وبالتالي هذا ما أريد أن أريكم إياه.
At the end, this head, this alien head,
في النهاية، هذه الرأس، هذه الرأس الغريبة،
is attached to the building platform,
متصلة بمنصة البناء،
and when the process is done, you just simply have to break the head
وعندما تنتهي العملية، عليك أن تفصل الرأس ببساطة
from the support structure you need,
من هيكل الدعم،
and then everything is ready.
وبعد ذلك كل شيء يكون جاهزًا.
So.
إذًا.
OK, but what does the microprinter look like?
لكن كيف تبدو الطابعة المتناهية الصغر؟
Well, maybe some of you have already seen this picture.
حسنًا، ربما رأى البعض منكم هذه الصورة.
I also brought it to you in person, so I want to kindly introduce you
أنا أيضا أحضرتها لكم، وأريد أن أقدم لكم
to the 3-D microprinter, which looks like this.
الطابعة ثلاثية الأبعاد متناهية الصغر والتي تبدو هكذا.
So it's very small, it's really a desktop version.
إنها صغيرة جدًا، إنها نسخة سطح المكتب.
It's a really affordable system.
إنها حقًا بأسعار في المتناول.
And we are really proud of it, actually, and --
وفي الواقع، نحن فخورون بها...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you have this tiny little system; there are bigger ones.
لديك هذا النظام الصغير، ويوجد أنظمة أكبر.
What can you do with a cheap, affordable system?
ماذا يمكن أن تفعل بنظام رخيص وأسعاره في المتناول؟
For example, you all know these hearing aids?
على سبيل المثال، كلكم تعرفون عن المعينات السمعية؟
They have to be produced individually for each person,
يجب تصنيعهم فرديًّا لكل شخص،
so this is a perfect example
لذلك هذا مثال رائع
for using this technology to create the shell for a hearing aid.
لاستخدام هذه التقنية في صنع قوقعة تساعد على السمع.
Normally, you go to the store, they scan your ear,
عادة تقوم بالذهاب إلى المتجر، ويقومون بفحص أذنك،
they send the data to Germany via email, and --
ثم يتم إرسال البيانات إلى ألمانيا عبر البريد الإلكتروني،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and then they print it out with a --
وبعد ذلك يتم طباعتها بواسطة،
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
Then they print it out with a big machine,
وبعد ذلك يقوموا بطباعتها بواسطة آلة كبيرة،
and then, when it's ready to send back to Vienna
وعندما تكون جاهزة لإرسالها مرة أخرى إلى فيينا
or wherever you are --
أو أينما كنت...
via post --
عبر البريد...
then they put in the electronics.
يقوموا بوضع الإلكترونيات.
When you have a microprinter in your store,
عندما تمتلك طابعة صغيرة في متجرك،
you can go to the store,
فيمكنك الذهاب للمتجر،
they scan your ear,
ليقوموا بفحص أذنك،
they just press "Print,"
وبمجرد الضغط على "طباعة،"
the 3-D model gets sliced,
تحصل على الشرائح ثلاثية الأبعاد للنموذج،
and you can go for a coffee,
ويمكنك الذهاب لتناول القهوة،
you can go to the university, whatever you want,
أو الذهاب للجامعة، مهما كان الذي تريده،
and instead of five days, you can have your ear shell or your hearing aid
وبدلًا من الانتظار 5 أيام، يمكنك الحصول على قوقعة الأذن أو المساعدات السمعية
in just one day.
في يوم واحد فقط.
And that is an example of how these tiny little machines
وهذا مثال على كيف أن هذه الآلات الصغيرة جدًا
or other cheap 3-D printers could change our everyday lives.
أو الطابعات الثلاثية الأبعاد الرخيصة تستطيع تغيير حياتنا اليومية.
So thank you very much,
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم،
and start printing whatever you want, whatever you need.
وابدأوا بطباعة ما تشاؤون، وتحتاجون إليه.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)